<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the King's most excellent  Maiesty. The humble petition of the commissionerrs of the General Assembly of the Kirk of Scotland, met at Edenborough Ianuary, 4. 1642.  And now lately presented to His Majesty, at Oxford.  With His Maiesties gratious answer thereunto March 16. 1642.</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08770</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4271BA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222782</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">64551097</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 64551097</idno>
            <idno type="VID">184470</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08770)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184470)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2864:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the King's most excellent  Maiesty. The humble petition of the commissionerrs of the General Assembly of the Kirk of Scotland, met at Edenborough Ianuary, 4. 1642.  And now lately presented to His Majesty, at Oxford.  With His Maiesties gratious answer thereunto March 16. 1642.</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], [14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Leonard Lichfield, Printer to the Vniversity,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed by His Majesties command at Oxford, March. 20. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Peterborough Cathedral.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of Scotland. --  General Assembly. --  Commission.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:184470:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184470:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TO THE KING'S MOST EXCELLENT MAIESTY. THE HUMBLE PETITION OF THE COMMISSIONERRS of the Generall Aſſembly of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> met at <hi>Edenborough Ianuary,</hi> 4. 1642. And now lately preſented to His Majeſty, At <hi>OXFORD.</hi> WITH HIS MAIESTIES Gratious Anſwer thereunto <hi>March</hi> 16. 1642.</p>
            <p>Printed by His MAjESTIES Command at <hi>OXFORD, March.</hi> 20. By LEONARD LICHFIELD, Printer to the <hi>Vniverſity.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:184470:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:184470:2"/>
            <head>TO THE KINGS MOST EXCELLENT MAJESTIE. The humble <hi>Petition</hi> of the <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> of the generall Aſſembly of the Kirk of SCOTLAND, met at <hi>Edenborough, Ian.</hi> 4. 1643.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr ſilence and ceaſing to preſent before your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty our humble thoughts and deſires at this time of common danger to Religion, to your Maieſties ſacred perſon, your Crowne and Poſterity, and to all your Majeſties Dominions, were impiety a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, unthankefulneſſe and diſloyalty againſt your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and indirect approbation and hardning of the Adverſaries of tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h and peace in their wicked wayes, and cruelty againſt our brethren, lying in ſuch depths of affliction and anguiſh of ſpirit. Any one of which crimes were in us, above all others, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable, and would prove us moſt unworthy of the truſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto us. The flame of this common combuſtion hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt devoured <hi>Ireland,</hi> is now waſting the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and we cannot tell how ſoone it ſhall enter upon our ſelves &amp; ſet this your <hi>Majeſties</hi> moſt ancient &amp; native Kingdom on fire: If in this wofull caſe &amp; lamentable condition of your Majeſties Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions al others ſhould be ſilent, it behoveth us to ſpeake; and if our Tongues and Penns ſhould ceaſe, our Conſciences within us would cry out, and the ſtones in the ſtreets would anſwer us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:184470:3"/>
Our great griefe and apprehenſion of danger is not a little increaſed, partly by the inſolency and preſumption of Papiſts and others diſaffected to the Reformation of Religion; who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though for their number and power they be not conſiderable amongſt us, yet through the ſucceſſe of the Popiſh party in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the hopes they conceive of the prevailing power of Popiſh Armies, and the Prelaticall Faction in <hi>England,</hi> they have of late taken ſpirit, and begun to ſpeak big words againſt the Reformation of Religion, and the work of God in this Land; and partly, and more principally, that a chiefe praiſe of the Prot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ant Religion (and thereby our not vaine, but juſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation) is by the publique Declaration of the Earle of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> Generall of Your Majeſties Forces for the Northerne parts, and neareſt unto us, transferred unto Papiſts. Who although they be ſworn Enemies unto Kings, and be as infamous for their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Conſpiracies againſt Princes and Rulers, as for their knowne Idolatry and ſpirituall Tyranny; yet are they openly declared to be not onely good Subjects, or better Subjects, but farre better Subjects then Proteſtants, which is a new and foule diſparagement of the reformed Religion, a notable injury to your <hi>Majeſty</hi> in your honor, a ſenſible reflection upon the whole body of this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> which is impatient that any ſubjects ſhould be more loyal then they; but abhorreth &amp; extreamly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daineth that <hi>Papiſts</hi> who refuſe to take the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> ſhould be compared with them in allegiance &amp; fidelity, &amp; (which being a ſtrange Doctrine from the mouth or pen of profeſſed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants) wil ſuffer a hard conſtruction from al thereformed <hi>Kirks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee therefore Your Majeſties moſt humble and loving Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, upon theſe and the like conſiderations, doe humbly intreat, that Your Majeſty may be pleaſed in Your Princely wiſedome, Firſt to conſider, that the intentions of Papiſts directed by the principles of their Profeſſion are no other then they have beene from the beginning, even to build their <hi>Babell,</hi> and to ſet up their execrable Idolatry and Antichriſtian Tyranny in all Your <hi>Majeſties</hi> Dominions, to change the face of your two Kingdoms of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England</hi> into the ſimilitude of miſerable <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> which is more bitter to the People of God, your Majeſties
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:184470:3"/>
good Subjects to thinke upon, then death: and whatſoever their preſent pretences be for the deſence of Your Majeſties Perſon, and Authority; yet in the end by their Armes and Power, with a diſplayed Banner, to bring that to paſſe againſt Your Royall Perſon and Poſterity, which the fifth of <hi>November</hi> (never to be forgotten) was not able by their ſubtill and undermining trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to produce; or which will be their greateſt mercy, to reduce Your Majeſty and Your Kingdomes to the baſe and unnaturall ſlavery of their Monarch the Pope.</p>
            <p>And next, that Your Majeſty upon this undeniable evidence, may timouſly, and ſpeedily apply your Royall Authority for disbanding their Forces, ſuppreſſing their power, and diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing their bloody and mercileſſe projects.</p>
            <p>And for this end we are with greater earneſtneſſe then before conſtrained, to fall downe againe before your Majeſty, and in all humility to renew the ſupplication of the late generall Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, and our owne former Petition in their name, for unity of Religion, and for uniformity of Church government, in all your Majeſties Kingdomes, &amp; to this effect for a meeting of ſome Divines to be holden in <hi>England;</hi> unto which according to the deſire of your Majeſties Parliament ſome Commiſſioners may be ſent from this Kirke, that in all points to be proponed and debated, there may be the greater conſent and harmony. Wee take the boldneſſe to be the more inſtant in this our humble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, becauſe it concerneth the Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſo much in his glory, your Majeſtie in your Honour, the Kirke of <hi>England</hi> (which wee ought to tender as our owne bowells, and whoſe reformation is more deare unto us, then our lives) in her happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the Kirke of <hi>Scotland</hi> in her purity and peace; former experience, and daily ſenſe teaching us, that without the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Kirk of <hi>England,</hi> there is no hope or poſſibility of the continuance of reformation here.</p>
            <p>The Lord of Heaven and Earth, whoſe Vice-gerent Your Majeſty is, calleth for this great worke of Reformation at Your hands, and the preſent commotions and troubles of your Majeſties Dominions, are either preparation in the mercy of God for this bleſſed reformation and Unity of Religion (which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:184470:4"/>
is the deſire, prayer, and expectation of all Your Majeſties good Subjects in this Kingdom) or which they tremble to think upon, and earneſtly deprecate, are in the Juſtice of God for the abuſe of the Goſpell, the tolerating of Idolatry, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition againſt ſo cleare a light, and not acknowledging the day of viſitation, the beginning of ſuch a dolefull deſolation, as no policy or power of man ſhall be able to prevent, and as ſhall make Your Majeſties Kingdomes within a ſhort time as miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as they may be happy by a reformation of Religion. God forbid, that whilſt the Houſes of Parliament doe profeſſe their deſire of the reformation of religion, in a peaceable and Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amentary way, and paſſe their Bills for that end in the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, that Your Majeſty, the Nurſe-Father of the Kirk of Chriſt, to whoſe care the cuſtody and vindication of religion doth principally belong, ſhall, to the provoking of the anger of God, the ſtopping of the influence of ſo many bleſſings from Heaven, and the grieving of the hearts of all the godly, fruſtrate our expectation, make our hopes aſhamed, and hazard the loſſe of the hearts of all Your good Subjects, which next unto the truth and unity of religion, and the ſafety of Your Kingdomes, are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to hazzard their lives, and ſpend their bloud for Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Honour, and Happineſſe.</p>
            <p>We are not ignorant that the worke is great, the difficulties and impediments many, and that there be both Mountaines and Lions in the way: the ſtrongeſt le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, till it be taken out of the way, is the Mountaine of <hi>Prelacy,</hi> and no wonder if Your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty conſider how many Papiſts, and Popiſhly affected, have for a long time found Peace and eaſe under the ſhadow thereof, how many of the Prelaticall Faction have thereby their life and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; how many prophane and wordly men doe feare the yoake of Chriſt? and are unwilling to ſubmit themſelves to the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Goſpell? and how many there be whoſe eyes are daz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the externall pompe and glory of the Kirke, whoſe mindes are miſcarried with a conceipt of the governing of the Kirke by the rules of humane policy, and whoſe hearts are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted with the apprehenſions of the dangerous conſequences which may enſue upon alterations. But when Your Majeſty in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:184470:4"/>
Your Princely and Religious Wiſedome, ſhall remember from the Records of former times, how againſt the gates of Hell, the force and fraude of worldly and wicked men, and all Panicke feares of danger, the Chriſtian Religion was firſt planted, and the Chriſtian Kirke thereafter reformed; and from the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the preſent times, how many from the experience of the tyranny of <hi>Prelates</hi> are afraid to diſcover themſelves, leſt they be revenged upon them hereafter? whereas <hi>Prelacy</hi> being remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved they would openly profeſſe what they are, and joyne with others in the way of Reformation. All obſtacles and difficulties ſhall be but matter of the manifeſtation of the power of God, the principall worker; and the meanes of the greater glory to Your Majeſty the prime inſtrument.</p>
            <p>The intermixture of the Government of <hi>Prelates,</hi> with the civill ſtate, mentioned in Your Majeſties Anſwer to our former Petition, being taken away, and the right government by Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, which is to bee ſeene in all the reformed Kirkes, and wherein the agreement will be eaſie, being ſettled; the Kirke and Religion will be more pure and free of mixture, and the civil Government more ſound and firme; that government of the kirk muſt ſuit beſt with the civill ſtate, and be moſt uſefull for <hi>Kings</hi> and Kingdoms, which is beſt warranted by God, by whom <hi>Kings</hi> doe raigne, and Kindomes are eſtabliſhed: Nor can a refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation be expected in the common and ordinary way, expeſſed alſo in Your Majeſties Anſwer; the wiſeſt and moſt religious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces have found it impoſſible, and implying a repugnancy, ſince the <hi>Perſons</hi> to be reformed, and the reformers muſt be divers, <hi>and the way</hi> of reformation muſt be different from the corrupt way, by which defection of workemen, and corruption in Doctrine, worſhip, and government, have entred into the Kirke. Suffer us therefore, dread Soveraigne, to renew our Petitions for this u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of religion, and uniformity of Kirke government, and for a meeting of ſome Divines of both Kingdomes who may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare matters for Your Majeſties view, and for the examination and approbation of more full aſſemblies; The Nationall aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of this Kirke, from which we have our Commiſſion, did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe in their thnkesgiving, for the many favours expreſſed in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:184470:5"/>
Your Majeſties Letter, their beſt endeavour to keepe the people under their charge in unity and peace, and in Loyalty and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Your Majeſty and Your Lawes, which we confeſſe is a duty well beſeeming the Preachers of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>But we cannot conceale how much both Paſtors and People are grieved and diſquieted, with the late reports of the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, boldneſſe and ſtrength of Popiſh forces in <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and how much danger from the power of ſo malicious and bloudy Enemies is apprehended, to the Religion and Peace of this Kirke and Kingdome, conceived by them to be the ſpring whence have iſſued all their calamities and miſeries: Which we humbly remonſtrate to Your Majeſty as a neceſſity requiring a generall Aſſembly, and do earneſtly ſupplicate for the preſence and aſſiſtance of Your Majeſties Commiſſioner at the day to be appointed, that by univerſall conſent of the whole Kirke, the beſt courſe may be taken for the preſervation of Religion, and for the averting of the great wrath which they conceive to be imminent to this Kingdom. If it ſhall pleaſe the Lord, in whoſe hand is the heart of the King, as the rivers of waters, to turne it whither ſoever he will, to incline Your Majeſties heart to this through reformation, no more to tolerate the Maſſe, or any part of romiſh ſuperſtition, or tyranny and to command that all good meanes be uſed for the converſion of Your Princely Conſort the Queenes Majeſty (which is alſo the humble deſire of this whole Kirke and Kingdom) Your Joynt comforts ſhall be mult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>plyed, above the dayes of Your affliction, to Your incredible joy, Your glory ſhall ſhine in brightneſſe, above all Your royall Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to the admiration of the world and the terror of Your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and Your Kingdomes ſo farre abound in righteouſneſſe, Peace and Proſperity, above all that hath beene in former Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, that they ſhall ſay, <hi>it is good for us that wee have beene afflicted.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:184470:5"/>
            <head>His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Anſwer to a late Petition preſented unto Him by the hands of <hi>Alexander Henderſon,</hi> from the Commisſioners of the generall Aſſembly of the Church of Scotland.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE received lately a Petition from you, by the hands of Mr. <hi>Alexander Henderſon,</hi> To the which We intended to have given an anſwer, as ſoone as Wee had tranſacted the buſineſſe with the other Commiſſioners addreſſed to us from the Conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Treaty of that our Kingdom. But finding the ſame to be publiſhed in Print, and to be diſperſed throughout Our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to the great danger of Scandalling of Our well-affected Subjects, who may interpret the bitterneſſe and ſharpeneſſe of ſome Expreſſions not to be ſo agreeable to that regard and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence which is due to our Perſon, and the matter it ſelfe to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull to the honour and conſtitution of this Kingdom, We have beene compelled the more ſtrictly to examine as well the Authority of the Petitioners, as the matter of the Petition it ſelfe, and to publiſh Our opinion of both, that Our Subjects of both Kingdomes may ſee how equally, juſt, and ſenſible We are of the Lawes and Honour of both Our Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>And firſt, upon peruſall of the Petition, We required to ſee the Commiſſion by which the meſſenger who brought this Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or the perſons who ſent him, are qualified to intermedle in Affaires ſo forraigne to their Juriſdiction, and of ſo great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment to this Our Kingdom of England. Vpon Examination whereof, and in defence of the Lawes and Government of this Our Kiingdom, which We are truſted and ſworn to defend, We muſt profeſſe that the Petitioners, or the generall Aſſembly of Our Church of Scotland have not the leaſt Authority or Power to intermeddle or interpoſe in the Affaires of this Kingdome or Church, which are ſetled and eſtabliſhed by the proper Lawes of this Land, and till they be altered by the ſame competent po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, cannot be enveighed againſt without a due ſence of Vs and this Nation, much leſſe can they preſent any advice or Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Our Houſes of Parliament againſt the ſame, or to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb facs="tcp:184470:6"/>
to ſend any letters, as they have now done, to any Miniſters of Our Church here, who by the Lawes of this Land cannot cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpond againſt the ſame. Therefore We doe believe that the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners, when they ſhall conſider how unwarranted it is by the Lawes of that Kingdom, and how contrary it is to the Lawes of this, to the profeſſions they have made to each other, and how becomming in it ſelfe for them to require the ancient, happy and eſtabliſhed government of the Church of England to be altered, and conformed to the Laws and conſtitutions of another Church will find themſelves miſled by the information of ſome factious perſons here, who would willingly ingage the Petitioners to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a difference and diviſion betweene the two Kingdomes, which We have with ſo much care and induſtry endeavoured to prevent, not having labour'd more to quench the combuſtion in this Kingdom, then We have to hinder the like from either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Ireland, or entring into Scotland, which if all others will equally labour, will undoubtedly be avoyded. But We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo eaſily paſſe over the mention of Ireland, being mov'd to it by ſcandalous Aſperſions, that have bin often caſt upon Vs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Subject, and the uſe that hath bin made of the woefull diſtractions of that Kingdom, as of a Seminary of feares and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies to beget the like diſtraction in this, and (which leaſt they may have farther influence) Wee are the more willing to make Our Innocence appeare in that particular.</p>
            <p>When firſt that horrid Rebellion began, Wee were in Our Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the ſenſe We had then of it, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions We made concerning it, the Commiſſions (together with ſome other Aſſiſtance) We ſent immediatly into that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the inſtant Recommendation We made of it to both Our Houſes of Parliament in England, are known to all perſons of quality there and then about Us. After Our return into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Our ready concurring to all the deſires of both Houſes that might moſt ſpeedily repreſſe that Rebellion, by pasſing the Bill of preſſing, and in it a clauſe which quitted a Right challenged by all, and enjoyed by many of Our Predeceſſors, by parting with Our Rights in the Lands eſcheated to Us by that Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for the encouragement of Adventurers, by emptying of Our Magazines of Armes and Ammunition for that ſervice (which We have ſince needed for Our neceſſary defence and preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) by conſenting to all Bills for the rayſing of mony for the
<pb facs="tcp:184470:6"/>
ſame, though containing unuſuall Clauſes, which truſted both Houſes without Vs with the matter of diſpoſing it, Our often preſſing both Houſes, not to neglect that Kingdom, by being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted by Conſiderations and Diſputes leſſe concerning both Kingdomes, Our offer of raiſing 10000. Voluntiers to bee ſent thither, and our ſeverall Offers to engage Our own Royall Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the ſuppreſſion of that horrid rebellion, are no leſſe known to all this Nation, then Our perpetuall earneſtneſſe by our For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Miniſters to keep all manner of ſupplies from being tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported for the reliefe of the Rebells, is known to ſeverall nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Princes. Which if all Our Subjects will conſider, and withall how many of the men, and how much of the money rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for that end, and how much Time, Care and Induſtry have been diverted from that employment, and imployed in this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall War againſt Vs, (the true cauſe of the preſent miſery and want which Our Brittiſh Armies there doe now endure) they will ſoon free Vs from al thoſe Imputations ſo ſcandalouſly and groundleſly laid upon us, and impute the continuance of the Combuſtion of that miſerable Kingdom, the danger it may bring upon our Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this dolefull deſolation, to thoſe who are truly guilty of it.</p>
            <p>For unity in Religion: which is deſired, We cannot but an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That We much apprehend leaſt the Papiſt may make ſome advantage of that expreſſion, by continuing that ſcandall with more Authority, which they have ever heretofore uſed to caſt upon the Reformation, by interpreting all the differences in Ceremony, Government, or indifferent opinions between ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Proteſtant Churches, to be differences in Religion; And leaſt our good Subjects of England, who have ever eſteemed themſelves of the ſame Religion with you, ſhould ſuſpect them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be eſteemed by you to bee of a contrary. And that the Religion which they and their Anceſtors have held ever ſince the bleſſed Reformation, and in and for which they are reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to dye, is taxed and branded of Falſehood or Inſufficiency, by ſuch a deſire.</p>
            <p>For uniformity in Church Government, We conceiv'd the Anſwer formerly given by Vs to the former Petition in this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, would have ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tisfied the Petitioners, and is ſo full, that We can adde little to it. <hi>viz. That the Government here eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<pb facs="tcp:184470:7"/>
by the lawes, hath ſo neer a relation and intermixture with the Civill State (which may be unknown to the Petitioners) that till a compoſed diſgeſted forme be preſented to us, upon a free debate of both Houſes in a Parliamentary way, whereby the conſent and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of this whole Kingdome may be had, and Wee, and all Our Subjects may diſcerne, what is to be left in, or brought in, as well as what is to be taken away, We know not how to conſent to any altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, otherwiſe then to ſuch an Act for the caſe of tender Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the matter of Ceremonies, as We have often offered; and that this, and any thing elſe that may concerne the Peace of the Church, and the Advancement of Gods true Religion may be ſoberly diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and happily effected; We have formerly offered, and are ſtill willing that debates of that nature may be enterd into by a Synod of Godly and Learned Divines to be regularly choſen according to the Laws and Cuſtomes of this Kingdom. To which We ſhall be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that ſome learned Divines of our Church of Scotland bee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſent, to be preſent, and offer and debate their Reaſons.</hi> With this Anſwer the Petitioners had great reaſon to acquiſce, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out enlarging the matter of their former Petition onely with bitter expresſions againſt the Eſtabliſhed Governement and Laws of their neighbour Nation, (as if it were contrary to the word of God) with whom they have ſo lately entred into a ſtrict Amity and Friendſhip.</p>
            <p>But We cannot enough wonder, that the Petitioners ſhould interpoſe themſelves, not only as fit Directors and Judges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Us and Our two Houſes of Parliament, in Buſineſſe ſo wholly concerning the Peace and Governement of this Our Kingdome, and in a matter ſo abſolutely entruſted to Us, as what new Laws to conſent or not to conſent to; But ſhould aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume and publiſh, That the deſire of Reformation in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is in a peaceable and Parliamentary way, When all the World may know, That the proceedings here, have beene and are not only contrary to all the rules and precedents of former Parliaments, but deſtructive to the Freedome, Priviledge, and Dignity of Parliaments themſelues; That We were firſt driven by tumults, for the ſafety of Our life, from Our Cities of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and have been ſince purſued, fought with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and are now kept from thence by an Army rayſed, as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, by the two Houſes, which conſiſt not of the fourth part of the number they ought to doe, the reſt being either driven
<pb facs="tcp:184470:7"/>
from thence by the ſame violence, or expelld or impriſoned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not conſenting to the Treaſons and unheard of Inſolencies pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed againſt Us; And if the Petitioners could believe theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings to be in a peaceable Parliamentary way, they were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unacquainted with the Order and conſtitution of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and not ſo fit inſtruments to promote that Reformation and Peace they ſeeme to deſire.</p>
            <p>We cannot beleeve the Intermixture of the preſent Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Government with the Civill State to be other then a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good reaſon, and that the government of the Church ſhould be by the rules of humane policy, to be other then a very good rule, unleſſe ſome other government were as well proved as pretended to be better warranted by God.</p>
            <p>Of any Bills offerd Us for Reformation, Wee ſhall not not now ſpeake, they being a part of thoſe Articles upon which We have offered and expect to Treat; But cannot but wonder by what authority you prejudg Our Judgment herein, by denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Gods anger upon Us, and Our hazard of the loſſe of the hearts of all Our good Subjects, if We conſent not unto them. The influence of ſo many bleſſings from heaven upon the regns of Queen <hi>Elizabath,</hi> and Our father of bleſſed memory, and the acknowledgment of them by all Proteſtant Churches to have been carefull Nurſes of the Church of Chriſt, and to have excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently diſcharged their duties in the cuſtody and vindication of Religion, and the affection of their Subjects to them, doe ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently aſſure Vs, that We ſhould neither ſtop the influence of ſuch Bleſſings, nor grieve the hearts of all the godly, nor hazard the loſſe of the hearts of Our good Subjects, although Wee ſtill maintain in this Kingdom the ſame eſtabliſht Eccleſiaſticall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which flouriſht in their times, and under their ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Protection.</p>
            <p>Wee doubt not but Our Subjects of Scotland will reſt aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſatisfied with ſuch alterations in their owne Church as We have aſſented unto, and not be perſwaded by a meer Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that there is no hope of the continuance of what is there ſetled by Law, unleſſe that be likewiſe altered which is ſetled here; And Our Subjects of England will never depart from their dutifull affection to U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, for not conſenting to new Laws, which by the law of the Land, they know, We may as juſty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject if We approve not of them, as either Houſe hath power to
<pb facs="tcp:184470:8"/>
prepare for, or both to propound to Vs. Nor are you a little mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken if either you believe the generality of this Nation to deſire a change of Church-government, or that moſt of thoſe who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it, deſire by it to introduce that which you onely eſteeme a Reformation, but are as unwilling to what you call the yoke of Chriſt and obedience to the Goſpell, as thoſe whom you cal prophane and worldly men, and ſo equally averſe both to Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy and Presbytery, that if they ſhould prevaile in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, the abolition of the one would be no let to the other, nor would your hearts be leſſe grieved, your expectations leſſe fruſtrated, your hopes leſſe aſhamed, or your Reformation more ſecured. And the Petitioners, upon due conſideration, will not find themſelves leſſe miſtaken in the government of all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, which they ſay is by Aſſemblies, then they are in the beſt way of a Reformation, which ſure is beſt to be in a common and ordinary way, where the paſſion or intereſt of particular men may not impoſe upon the publique, but alteration be then only made, when, upon calme Debates, and evident and cleare Reaſon and convenience, the ſame ſhall be generally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to for the peace and ſecurity of the people, and thoſe who are truſted by the Law with ſuch debates, are not diveſted of that truſt upon a generall charge of corruptions pretended to have entred by that way, and of being the perſons to be refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and ſo unfit to be Reformers. And certainly the like Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke with the like charges and pretences might be us'd to make the parliament it ſelfe ano incapable Iudge of any Reformation either in Church or State.</p>
            <p>For the generall Expreſſions in the Petition againſt Papiſts, in which the Petitioners may be underſtood to charge Vs with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance and favour even to their opinions, We have taken all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to publiſh to the world Our practice and Reſolution in the true Proteſtant Reformed Religion, and we are verily perſwaded there is no one Subject in either of Our Dominions, who at all knowes Vs, and hath obſerved Our Life, but is in his Soule ſatisfied of Our Zeale and unremoveable Affection to that Religion, and of Our true diſlike of and hearty opoſition to popery, And as we willingly c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſented, at our being in Scotland, to all Acts propoſed to Vs, for the diſcountenancing and Reforming the Papiſts in that our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſo by Our Proclamations for the putting of all Lawes ſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in execution againſt Recuſants, and by not refuſing any one
<pb facs="tcp:184470:8"/>
Bill preſented to Vs to that purpoſe in this Kingdome, and by Our perpetuall and publique profeſſions of Readineſſe with the Advice of Our two Houſes of Parliament prepared for Vs in a deliberate and orderly way, to find ſome expedition to perfect ſo good a work, Or conceiv'd we had not left it poſſible for any man to believe Vs guilty of tolerating any part of the Romiſh Tyranny or Supe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or to ſuſpect that the Converſion of Our deareſt Conſort, was not ſo much Our deſire, that the Acceſſion of as many Crownes, as God hath already beſtowed upon us, would be more welcome to us then that day: A Bleſſing which it is Our daily prayer to the Almighty to beſtow upon Vs.</p>
            <p>But We might well have expected from the Petitioners, who have in their ſolemne Nationall Covenant literally ſworne ſo much Care of the ſafety of Our Perſon, and cannot but know in how much danger that hath bin and ſtill is by the power and threats of Rebellious Armes, that they would as well have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred the 23. of October, as the 5. of November, and as well have taken notice of the Army raiſed and led againſt Vs by the Earle of Eſſex, which hath actually aſſaulted and endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to murther Vs, which Wee know to abound in Browniſts, Anabaptiſts, and other Sectaries, and in which Wee have reaſon (by the priſoners We have taken, and the Evidence they have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) to believe there are many more Papiſts (and many of thoſe forraigners) then in all Our Army, as have adviſed Vs to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band out of the Army of the Earle of New-caſtle, which is raiſed for Our defence, the papiſts in that Army, who are known to be no ſuch number as to endanger their obtaining any power of building their <hi>Babell,</hi> and ſetting up their Idolatry, and whoſe Loyalty he hath reaſon to commend) though hee was never ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected for favouring their Religion) not before that of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, but of ſuch as rebell under that Title; And whoſe aſſiſtance is as due to us by the Law of God, and Man, to reſcue Vs from domeſtique Rebellion, as to defend Vs from forraigne invaſion, which We thinke no man denies to be lawfull for them to doe, But We doe ſolemnly declare and proteſt, That God ſhall no ſooner free Vs from the deſperate and rebellious Armes taken up againſt Vs, but We ſhall endeavour to free Our ſelves and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from any feare of danger from the other, by diſarming them according to the Lawes of this Land, as We ſhall not faile to ſend Our Commisſioner to the Aſſembly at the time appointed for it by the Lawes of Scotland:</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:184470:9"/>
To conclude, We deſire and require the Petitioners (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes good and pious Preachers of the Goſpell) to uſe their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt endeavours to compoſe any diſtraction in opinions, or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtandings, which may by the Faction of ſome turbulent perſons, be raiſed in the mindes of Our good Subjects of that Our Kingdom, and to infuſe into them a true ſence of Charity, Obedience and Humility, the great principles of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; That they may not ſuffer themſelves to bee tranſported with things they doe not underſtand, or think themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the Governmenn of another Kingdom, becauſe it is not according to the cuſtomes of that in which they live; But that they diſpoſe themſelves with modeſty and devotion to the ſervice of Almighty God, with duty and affection to tue obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Vs and Our Lawes (remembring the ſingular Grace, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and Benignity We have alwaies expreſſed to that Our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Kingdom) and with Brotherly and Chriſtian Charity one towards another; And We doubt not but God in his mercy to Vs and them will make Vs Inſtruments of his Blesſings upon each other, and both of Us a great meaſure of Happineſſe and Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity to the whole Nation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:184470:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
